By now you've seen all
到目前为止 你已经了解到了
of the main pieces of the
推荐系统算法或者
recommender system algorithm or the collaborative filtering algorithm.
协同过滤算法的所有要点
In this video I want
在这节视频中
to just share one last implementational detail,
我想分享最后一点实现过程中的细节
namely mean normalization, which
这一点就是均值归一化
can sometimes just make the
有时它可以让算法
algorithm work a little bit better.
运行得更好
To motivate the idea of mean normalization, let's
为了了解均值归一化这个想法的动机
consider an example of where
我们考虑这样一个例子
there's a user that has not rated any movies.
有一个用户没有给任何电影评分
So, in addition to our
加上之前我们有四个用户
four users, Alice, Bob, Carol,
Alice Bob Carol 和 Dave
and Dave, I've added a
我现在加上了第五个用户 Eve
fifth user, Eve, who hasn't rated any movies.
她没有给任何电影评分
Let's see what our collaborative filtering
我们来看看协同过滤算法
algorithm will do on this user.
会对这个用户做什么
Let's say that n is equal to 2 and so
假如说 n 等于2
we're going to learn two features
所以我们要学习两个特征变量
and we are going to have
我们要学习出
to learn a parameter vector theta
一个参数向量θ(5)
5, which is going to be
这是一个二维向量
in R2, remember this
提醒一下
is now vectors in Rn not Rn+1,
这个向量是 n 维的 而不是 n+1 维的
we'll learn the parameter vector theta 5 for our user number 5, Eve.
我们要学习5号用户 Eve 的参数向量 θ(5)
So if we look in
如果我们看
the first term in this
这个优化目标的
optimization objective, well the
第一项
user Eve hasn't rated any
用户 Eve 没给任何电影打过分
movies, so there are
所以对用户 Eve 来说
no movies for
没有电影
which Rij is equal to
满足 r(i,j)=1
one for the user Eve and
这个条件
so this first term plays no
所以这第一项
role at all in determining theta 5
完全不影响 θ(5) 的值
because there are no movies that Eve has rated.
因为没有电影被 Eve 评过分
And so the only term that
所以影响 θ(5) 值的唯一一项
effects theta 5 is this term.
是这一项
And so we're saying that we
这就是说
want to choose vector theta 5 so
我们想选一个向量 θ(5)
that the last regularization term is
使得最后的正则化项
as small as possible.
尽可能地小
In other words we want to minimize this
换句话说 我们想要最小化这个式子
lambda over 2 theta 5 subscript 1 squared
λ/2[(θ(5)_1)^2+(θ(5)_2)^2]
plus theta 5
subscript 2 squared so
λ/2[(θ(5)_1)^2+(θ(5)_2)^2]
that's the component of the
它们是和用户5有关的
regularization term that corresponds to
正则化项的要素
user 5, and of course
当然
if your goal is to
如果你的目标是
minimize this term, then
最小化这一项
what you're going to end up
那么你最终得到的
with is just theta 5 equals 0 0.
就会是 θ(5)=[0;0]
Because a regularization term
因为正则化项
is encouraging us to set
会让你的参数
parameters close to 0
接近0
and if there is
如果没有数据
no data to try to
能够使得参数
pull the parameters away from
远离0
0, because this first term
因为这第一项
doesn't effect theta 5,
不影响 θ(5) 值
we just end up with theta 5
我们就会得到
equals the vector of all zeros. And
θ(5) 等于零向量的结果
so when we go to
所以当我们要预测
predict how user 5 would
用户5会如何
rate any movie, we have
给电影打分
that theta 5 transpose xi,
我们有 θ(5) 转置乘以 x(i)
for any i, that's just going
对任意i
to be equal to zero.
结果都会等于0
Because theta 5 is 0 for any value of
因为对任意x值 θ(5) 都是0
x, this inner product is going to be equal to 0. And what we're
这个内积就会等于0
going to have therefore, is that
因此我们得到的结果是
we're going to predict that Eve
我们会预测
is going to rate every single
Eve 给所有电影的评分
movie with zero stars.
都是零星
But this doesn't seem very useful does it?
但是这个结果看起来没什么用吧？
I mean if you look at the different movies,
我的意思是 如果你看不同的电影
Love at Last, this first movie,
《爱到最后》 这第一个电影
a couple people rated it 5 stars.
两个人给它评了五星
And for even the Swords vs. Karate, someone rated it 5 stars.
甚至对《剑与空手道》 也有人评了五星
So some people do like some movies.
所以某些人确实喜欢某些电影
It seems not useful to
看起来只是预测
just predict that Eve is going to rate everything 0 stars.
Eve 会给他们全部评零星是没用的
And in fact if we're predicting
而且实际上如果我们预测
that eve is going to rate everything 0 stars,
Eve 会给所有电影零星的话
we also don't have any
我们还是没有任何好方法
good way of recommending any movies
来把电影推荐给她
to her, because you know
因为你知道
all of these movies are getting exactly the
预测结果是所有这些电影
same predicted rating for Eve
都会被 Eve 给出一样的评分
so there's no one movie with
所以没有一部电影
a higher predicted rating that
拥有高一点儿的预测评分
we could recommend to her, so, that's not very good.
让我们能推荐给她 所以这不太好
The idea of mean normalization will let us fix this problem.
均值归一化的想法可以让我们解决这个问题
So here's how it works.
下面介绍它是如果工作的
As before let me group all of my
和以前一样
movie ratings into this matrix
我们把所有评分放到矩阵Y里
Y, so just take all of
就是把所有这些评分
these ratings and group them
全部整合到矩阵Y中
into matrix Y.  And this
这边这列
column over here of all
全部是问号的这列
question marks corresponds to
对应的是
Eve's not having rated any movies.
Eve 没有给任何电影评分
Now to perform mean normalization what I'm going to
现在要实现均值归一化
do is compute the average
我要做的就是计算
rating that each movie obtained.
每个电影所得评分的均值
And I'm going to store that
我要把它们存在一个向量中
in a vector that we'll call mu.
我们称这个向量为 μ
So the first movie got two 5-star and two 0-star ratings,
所以第一个电影得到了两个5星和两个0星的评价
so the average of that is a 2.5-star rating.
均值就是2.5星评价
The second movie had
第二个电影的平均评价
an average of 2.5-stars and so on.
是2.5星 等等
And the final movie that has 0, 0, 5, 0.
最后一个电影的评分是 0 0 5 0
And the average of 0, 0,
0 0 5 0 的平均值
5, 0, that averages out to
an average of 1.25
就是1.25星评价
rating. And what I'm going to
我要做的事
do is look at all
要把所有的电影评分
the movie ratings and I'm going
to subtract off the mean rating.
减去平均评分
So this first element 5 I'm going to subtract off 2.5 and that gives me 2.5.
所以这第一个元素5 我要减去2.5 等于2.5
And the second element 5 subtract off of 2.5,
第二个元素5 减去2.5
get a 2.5.
得到2.5
And then the 0,
然后是0 0
0, subtract off 2.5 and you get -2.5, -2.5.
减去2.5 得到-2.5 -2.5
In other words, what
换句话说
I'm going to do is take
我要做的就是
my matrix of movie ratings,
把我的电影评分矩阵
take this wide matrix, and
也就是这个Y矩阵
subtract form each row the average rating for that movie.
把它的每一行都减去那个电影的平均评分
So, what I'm doing is
所以我做的就是
just normalizing each movie to
把每个电影都归一化为
have an average rating of zero.
平均评分为零
And so just one last example.
最后一个例子
If you look at this last row, 0 0 5 0.
如果你看最后一行 0 0 5 0
We're going to subtract 1.25, and
我们要减去1.25
so I end up with
最后我得到
these values over here.
那边这些值
So now and of course
那么现在
the question marks stay a question
当然这些问号没变
mark.
还是问号
So each movie in
所以每个电影
this new matrix Y has
在新矩阵Y中的
an average rating of 0.
平均评分都是0
What I'm going to do then, is
接下来我要做的就是
take this set of ratings
对这个评分数据集
and use it with my collaborative filtering algorithm.
使用协同过滤算法
So I'm going to pretend that this
所以我要假设
was the data that I had
这就是我从用户那儿
gotten from my users, or pretend that
得到的数据
these are the actual ratings I
或者假设它们就是
had gotten from the users, and I'm
我从用户那儿得到的实际评分
going to use this as my
我要把这个当做我的数据集
data set with which to
用它来学习
learn my parameters theta
我的参数 θ(j)
J and my features XI
和特征变量 x(i)
- from these mean normalized movie ratings.
就是用这些均值归一化后的电影评分来学习
When I want to make predictions
当我想要做
of movie ratings, what I'm
电影评分预测时
going to do is the
我要做的步骤如下
following:  for user J on movie
对用户j对电影i的评分
I, I'm gonna predict theta
我要预测它为
J transpose XI, where
θ(j) 转置乘以 x(i)
X and theta are the parameters
其中 x 和 θ 都是
that I've learned from this mean normalized data set.
均值归一化的数据集中学习出的参数
But, because on the data
但是因为我已经对数据集
set, I had subtracted off the
减去了均值
means in order to make
所以为了
a prediction on movie i,
给电影i预测评分
I'm going to need to add back in the mean,
我要把这个均值加回来
and so i'm going to add
所以我要再加回 μi
back in mu i. And
so that's going to be
所以这就是
my prediction where in my training
我得到的预测值
data subtracted off all the
因为训练数据减去了所有的均值
means and so when we
所以当我做预测时
make predictions and we need
我们需要
to add back in these
给电影 i
means mu i for movie i.  And
加回这个均值 μi
so specifically if you user
具体来说
5 which is Eve, the same argument as
如果用户5 Eve
the previous slide still applies in
之前幻灯片里的的描述仍然成立
the sense that Eve had
Eve 从来没有
not rated any movies and
给任何电影打分
so the learned parameter for
所以学习到的用户5的参数
user 5 is still going to
仍然还是
be equal to 0, 0.
会等于 0 0
And so what we're
所以我们会得到的是
going to get then is that
on a particular movie i we're
对特定的电影 i
going to predict for Eve theta
我们预测 Eve 的评分是
5, transpose xi plus
θ(5) 转置乘以 x(i)
add back in mu i and
然后再加上 μi
so this first component is
所以如果 θ(5) 等于0的话
going to be equal to zero, if theta five is equal to zero.
这第一部分就会等于0
And so on movie i, we
所以对电影 i 的评分
are going to end a predicting mu
我们最终会预测为 μi
i. And, this actually makes sense.
这实际上是说得通的
It means that
它的意思是
on movie 1 we're
对于电影 1
going to predict Eve rates it 2.5.
我们会预测 Eve 对它的评分是2.5
On movie 2 we're gonna predict Eve rates it 2.5.
对于电影2 我们会预测 Eve 给它2.5星
On movie 3 we're
对于电影3
gonna predict Eve rates it at 2
我们会预测 Eve 给它2星
and so on.
依次类推
This actually makes sense, because it says
这其实说得通
that if Eve hasn't rated
因为它的意思是
any movies and we just
如果 Eve 没给任何电影评分
don't know anything about this new
我们就对这个新用户 Eve 一无所知
user Eve, what we're going
我们要做的就是预测
to do is just predict for
她对每个电影的评分
each of the movies, what are
就是这些电影所得的平均评分
the average rating that those movies got.
Finally, as an aside, in
最后再补充一下
this video we talked about mean
在这个视频中
normalization, where we normalized
我们谈到了均值归一化
each row of the matrix y,
我们归一化矩阵Y
to have mean 0.
使得每行的均值都是0
In case you have some movies
如果有些电影是没有评分的
with no ratings, so it is
这个情形类似于
analogous to a user who hasn't rated anything,
有的用户没有给任何电影评分的情况
but in case you have some
但是如果你有些电影
movies with no ratings, you
是没有评分的
can also play with versions
你可以尝试这个算法的其他版本
of the algorithm, where you
你可以对不同的列
normalize the different columns
进行归一化
to have means zero, instead of
使得它们的均值为0
normalizing the rows to have mean
而不是把行均值归一化为0
zero, although that's maybe
虽说这个可能不太重要
less important, because if you
因为如果你
really have a movie with no
真的有个电影没有评分
rating, maybe you just
可能不管怎么说
shouldn't recommend that movie to anyone, anyway.
你就不该把这个电影推荐给任何人
And so, taking
所以说
care of the case of a user who hasn't
解决用户没评价过
rated anything might be more
任何电影的状况
important than taking care of
可能比解决
the case of a movie
电影没被评价过
that hasn't gotten a single rating.
的状况更重要
So to summarize, that's how
最后总结一下
you can do mean normalization as
这就是可以说是作为协同过滤算法的预处理步骤
a sort of pre-processing step for collaborative filtering.
均值归一化的实现
Depending on your data set,
根据你的数据集的不同
this might some times make your implementation
它可能有时会让实现的算法
work just a little bit better.
表现得好一点儿 (字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )